If your child struggles with math
anxiety, it’s important to
understand what it is. Having an
understanding of their emotional
reactions to math class and/or math
homework can be beneficial to
helping them work through it.
Extreme math anxiety is prevalent
in about 2-6% of secondary-school
level children. Less extreme math
anxiety is more common and can also
have a severe negative impact on
your children.
According to the University of
Cambridge Center for Neuroscience
in Education, math anxiety is, “a
negative emotional reaction to
mathematics that can be
debilitating”. Math anxiety has
also been defined as “a feeling of
tension and anxiety that interferes
with the manipulation of numbers
and the solving of mathematical
problems in … ordinary life and
academic situations”. Someone who
struggles with math anxiety can
have a very hard time learning,
practicing and applying math in
school and out.
Math anxiety not only affects your
children in school, but can also
have an effect on their everyday
lives. Children who struggle with
untreated math anxiety can develop
an avoidance to real-world
situations in which anything with
numbers or math is involved. This
can even influence what careers
they choose later on. Math anxiety
has been shown to correlate with
poor performance in math class
which can impact your child’s
overall attitude towards school.
Some signs that your child
struggles with math anxiety can
include negative-self talk
surrounding math, putting off math
work, panic when doing math
homework, and lack of motivation to
work on math. If this sounds like
your child, there are ways in which
you can help them to overcome their
math anxiety.
Encouraging positive self-talk
about math is a good place to
start. If your child begins to put
themselves down about their math
abilities, attempt to change the
tone of the conversation to a
positive one. Uplifting your child
about their math skills can help to
change their overall attitude about
math.
Another way to help your child is
to schedule times during the week
when they will work on math, either
independently or with the help of a
tutor. Scheduling tutoring sessions
can be an efficient way to ensure
that your child is consistently
practicing their math skills.
Getting organized, having a
schedule, and including extra help
for your child’s math lessons can
have significant effects on their
math anxiety and performance.
Working with a tutor to clear up
any confusion before math class or
exams will reduce their anxiety
about math greatly.
Online tutoring resources that are
flexible and affordable are
available with Access2Success.
Personalized tutoring plans for
your children’s math curriculum can
reduce their math anxiety, improve
their performance, and facilitate a
positive attitude surrounding math.